Let us begin by looking at a right-angled triangle. This is
a three-four-five triangle, one of the most well-known examples in mathematics.
We can draw squares on each side of the triangle.
The blue square on side a, the green square on
side b, and the red square on the hypotenuse c.
The Pythagorean theorem states that a squared plus b squared
equals c squared. The area of the two smaller squares
together equals the area of the largest square.
Now let us prove this visually by counting areas. A three-by-three
square has nine unit cells. A four-by-four square has sixteen unit
cells. And the hypotenuse square, five-by-five, has twenty-five cells.
Let us now move the nine blue cells from
a-squared into the top-left corner of the c-squared grid.
Now we move the sixteen green cells from
b-squared into the remaining L-shaped region of c-squared.
All twenty-five cells fit perfectly! Nine plus sixteen equals
twenty-five. This proves a-squared plus b-squared equals c-squared.
Now let us prove this algebraically. We construct a large square whose
side length is a plus b. Inside this square, we place four
identical right triangles, each with sides a and b and hypotenuse c.
The area of the large square is a plus b, the
whole squared. This equals the area of the inner c-squared, plus
the four triangles, each of area one-half a b.
Expanding the left side, we get a squared plus two a b plus b
squared. And the right side simplifies to c squared plus two a b.
Now, let us strip off the four triangles from the
diagram. Watch as they slide away from the square.
Subtracting two a b from both sides, we are
left with a squared plus b squared equals c
squared. And that is the Pythagorean theorem, proved!